3-42, Athabasca Hall, Edmonton, Alberta, T6G 2E8, Canada

■ karim.ali@ualberta.ca | A karimali.ca | karimhamdanali | M @karimhamdanali

Research Areas

My primary research interest is to develop and evaluate various program analysis techniques that can be used in practice by exploring three aspects: scalability, precision, and usability. My interests span programming languages and software systems.

Education

Ph.D., Computer Science 2014

UNIVERSITY OF WATERLOO, CANADA

- · Advisor: Ondřej Lhoták
- Thesis: The Separate Compilation Assumption
- · Committee: Jan Vitek, Frank Tip, Reid Holmes, and Werner Dietl

MMath, Computer Science 2010

University of Waterloo, Canada

- · Advisor: Raouf Boutaba
- Thesis: Algorizmi A Configurable Virtual Testbed to Generate Datasets for Offline Evaluation of Intrusion Detection Systems
- Reviewers: Ian MacKillop and Urs Hengartner

B.Sc., Computer Science

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

- · Advisors: Sherif G. Aly and Sherif El-Kassas
- Thesis: A Jabber Framework for Building Communication Capable Java Mobile Applications
- · Minor: Mathematics

Professional Experience

Assistant Professor, Department of Computing Science

University of Alberta, Canada

Research Assistant Professor, Department of Computing Science

University of Alberta, Canada

Postdoctoral Researcher, Secure Software Engineering

TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY

- · Host: Eric Bodden
- Designing novel static analyses to detect misuses of cryptographic APIs in software systems
- Exploring new static analysis techniques that incorporate user feedback in a just-in-time fashion
- · Developing various extensions to the IFDS analysis framework

Graduate Research Assistant, Programming Languages Group

University of Waterloo, Canada

- Conducted research for constructing partial static call graphs for Java programs
- Developed various call graph construction algorithms for Scala
- Studied static analysis techniques for various JVM-hosted languages

Graduate Research Assistant, Network Security Research Group

University of Waterloo, Canada

· Worked on various models of Intrusion Detection Systems: e.g., peer-to-peer, kernel methods

• Developed Algorizmi, an open-source evaluation system for Intrusion Detection Systems

Researcher, Department of Computer Science

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

· Studied new techniques to support location management in Java-based pervasive systems

Jul 2017-Present

Jul 2016-Jul 2017

Oct 2014-Jul 2016

2007

2010-2014

2008-2009

2012

ITWORX, EGYPT

· Redesigned the graphical user interface of the stock brokerage system for Execution Ltd., London, UK

Awards and Honors

ACM SIGPLAN Distinguished Paper Award 2019

ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages

Student's Choice Award 2018

UNIVERSITY OF ALBERTA

ACM SIGSOFT Distinguished Paper Award 2017

INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM ON SOFTWARE TESTING AND ANALYSIS

Distinguished Artifact Award 2014

EUROPEAN CONFERENCE ON OBJECT-ORIENTED PROGRAMMING

David R. Cheriton Scholarship 2012-2014 University of Waterloo, Canada \$20,000

Special Graduate Scholarship

University of Waterloo, Canada \$2,500

Queen Elizabeth II Graduate Scholarship in Science and Technology 2012

CANADA \$5,000

Special Graduate Scholarship 2011 University of Waterloo, Canada \$1,000

Graduate Entrance Scholarship 2008 University of Waterloo, Canada \$3,000

B.Sc. Summa Cum Laude Honors 2007

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

Best CS Group Graduation Project Award

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT

Shell Endowed Scholarship

THE AMERICAN UNIVERSITY IN CAIRO, EGYPT 30% off tuition

Professional Service

PROGRAM COMMITTEE ORGANIZATION

PLMW Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Systems, Programming, Languages and Applications: Software for Humanity (SPLASH)

SPLASH-I Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Systems, Programming, Languages and Applications: Software for Humanity (SPLASH) 2018

SPLASH-I Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Systems, Programming, Languages and Applications: Software for Humanity (SPLASH) 2017

Artifact Evaluation Co-Chair, International Symposium on Engineering Secure Software and Systems (ESSoS) 2017

Demonstration Track Co-Chair, ACM SIGSOFT Symposium on the Foundations of Software Engineering (FSE) 2017

Program Committee Co-Chair, ACM SIGPLAN International Workshop on the State Of the Art in Program Analysis (SOAP) @ PLDI 2017

PROGRAM COMMITTEE MEMBER

SOAP @ PLDI, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation 2019

ISSTA, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis 2019 **ECOOP**, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming 2018

ISSTA, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis 2018

CASCON, International Conference on Computer Science and Software Engineering 2017 Onward!, ACM International Symposium on New Ideas, New Paradigms, and Reflections on Programming and Software 2017

2/6 KARIM ALI · CURRICULUM VITAE **FEBRUARY 1, 2019**

ARTIFACT EVALUATION COMMITTEE MEMBER

Publications	
Coarse-Grained Call Graph Analysis of Android Applications Huawei Innovation Research Program (HIRP) With: Sole PI Amount: USD\$46,200	2017–2018
Improving the Inlining Algorithms in the IBM Just-in-Time (JIT) Compiler • IBM Centre for Advanced Studies Research Fellowship • With: Sole PI • Amount: CAD\$60,000	2017–2020
 Scalable and Precise Program Analysis for Modern Software Systems Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC) Discovery Grant With: Sole PI Amount: CAD\$125,000 	2017–2022
Validating the Correct Usage of Cryptography Libraries • IBM Centre for Advanced Studies Research Fellowship • With: Sole PI • Amount: CAD\$30,000	2018–2020
Research Funding	
Steering Committee Member, Undergraduate Capstone Open Source Projects (UCOSP) Faculty Mentor, Undergraduate Capstone Open Source Projects (UCOSP) Associate Editor, IEEE Software Blog Web Chair, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming (ECOOP) Web Chair, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis (ISSTA) Subreviewer, International Conference on Compiler Construction (CC)	2018 2018 2017–Present 2018 2018 2017
OTHER	
TSE, IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering TOPLAS, ACM Transactions on Programming Languages and Systems SCP, Science of Computer Programming	2013, 2019 2018 2015
Reviewer	
Co-Organizer, Program Analysis Hackathon (Panathon) @ ECOOP/ISSTA Co-Organizer, Workshop on Benchmarking (BenchWork) @ ECOOP/ISSTA Co-Organizer, Compiler-Driven Performance Workshop @ CASCON Co-Organizer, SOAP @ PLDI Co-Organizer, WALA Hackathon @ PLDI Co-Organizer, Workshop on Designing Code Analysis Frameworks (DECAF) @ ISSTA Co-Organizer, Workshop on WALA @ PLDI	2018 2018 2017 2017 2016 2015
Workshop Organization	
ISSTA, International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis PLDI, ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation ECOOP, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming ECOOP, European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming	2016 2015 2015 2014

Publications _

REFEREED JOURNAL ARTICLES

Johannes Späth, Karim Ali, and Eric Bodden. "Context-, Flow-, and Field-Sensitive Data-Flow Analysis Using Synchronized Pushdown Systems". PACMPL, 3(POPL), 48:1–48:29, 2019.

POPL '19 Distinguished Paper

Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, Stefan Krüger, Patrick Hill, Karim Ali, and Eric Bodden. "Debugging Static Analysis". IEEE TSE '18 Transactions on Software Engineering, (to appear), 2018. Johannes Späth, **Karim Ali**, and Eric Bodden. "IDE^{al}: Efficient and Precise Alias-Aware Dataflow Analysis". *PACMPL*. OOPSLA '17 1(OOPSLA), 99:1–99:27, 2017. Karim Ali, Marianna Rapoport, Ondřej Lhoták, Julian Dolby, and Frank Tip. "Type-Based Call Graph Construction TOSEM '15 Algorithms for Scala". ACM Transactions on Software Engineering and Methodology, 25(1), 9:1–9:43, 2015. Sherif Aly, Sarah Nadi, and Karim Hamdan. "A Java-Based Programming Language Support of Location Manage-IJCSNS '08 ment in Pervasive Systems". International Journal of Computer Science and Network Security, 8(6), pp. 329–336, 2008. REFEREED CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS Stefan Krüger, Johannes Späth, Karim Ali, Eric Bodden, and Mira Mezini. "CrySL: An Extensible Approach to Val-**ECOOP** '18 idating the Correct Usage of Cryptographic APIs". European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming, 10:1-10:27, 2018. Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, Stefan Krüger, Patrick Hill, Karim Ali, and Eric Bodden. "VISUFLOW: A Debugging Envi-ICSE '18 ronment for Static Analyses". International Conference on Software Engineering (Companion Volume), pp. 89–92, Tool Paper 2018. Stefan Krüger, Sarah Nadi, Michael Reif, Karim Ali, Mira Mezini, Eric Bodden, Florian Göpfert, Felix Günther, Chris-**ASE** '17 tian Weinert, Daniel Demmler, and Ram Kamath. "CogniCrypt: Supporting Developers in using Cryptography". Tool Paper *International Conference on Automated Software Engineering*, pp. 931–936, 2017. Mona Nashaat, Karim Ali, and James Miller. "Detecting Security Vulnerabilities in Object-Oriented PHP Programs". SCAM '17 IEEE International Working Conference on Source Code Analysis and Manipulation, pp. 159–164, 2017. Taylor Lloyd, Artem Chikin, Erick Ochoa, **Karim Ali**, and J Nelson Amaral. "A Case for Better Integration of Host and FSP '17 Target Compilation When Using OpenCL for FPGAs". International Workshop on FPGAs for Software Programmers, pp. 1-9, 2017. Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, Karim Ali, Ben Livshits, Eric Bodden, Justin Smith, and Emerson Murphy-Hill. "Just-in-ISSTA '17 Time Static Analysis". International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis, pp. 307–317, 2017. Distinguished Paper Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, Karim Ali, Ben Livshits, Eric Bodden, Justin Smith, and Emerson Murphy-Hill. "Cheetah: ICSE '17 Just-in-Time Taint Analysis for Android Apps". International Conference on Software Engineering - Companion Vol-Tool Paper ume, pp. 39-42, 2017. Johannes Späth, Lisa Nguyen Quang Do, Karim Ali, and Eric Bodden. "Boomerang: Demand-Driven Flow-ECOOP '16 Sensitive, Field-Sensitive, and Context-Sensitive Pointer Analysis". European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming, 22:1–22:26, 2016. Steven Arzt, Sarah Nadi, Karim Ali, Eric Bodden, Sebastian Erdweg, and Mira Mezini. "Towards Secure Integration Onward! '15 of Cryptographic Software". ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on New Ideas in Programming and Reflections on Software at SPLASH, pp. 1-13, 2015. Karim Ali, Marianna Rapoport, Ondřej Lhoták, Julian Dolby, and Frank Tip. "Constructing Call Graphs of Scala ECOOP '14 Programs". European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming, pp. 54–79, 2014. Distinguished Artifact Karim Ali and Ondřej Lhoták. "Averroes: Whole-Program Analysis without the Whole Program". European Confer-ECOOP '13 ence on Object-Oriented Programming, pp. 378–400, 2013. Karim Ali and Ondřej Lhoták. "Application-Only Call Graph Construction". European Conference on Object-Oriented **ECOOP** '12 Programming, pp. 688-712, 2012.

OTHER REFEREED PUBLICATIONS

Karim Ali, Issam Aib, and Raouf Boutaba. "P2P-AIS: A P2P Artificial Immune Systems architecture for detecting DDoS flooding attacks". *Global Information Infrastructure Symposium*, 2009.

Karim Ali and Raouf Boutaba. "Applying Kernel Methods to Anomaly-based Intrusion Detection Systems". *Global Information Infrastructure Symposium*, 2009.

Students_

CURRENT

Ifaz Kabir 2018–Present

University of Alberta, Canada Ph.D.

Abdul Ali Bangash 2018–Present

University of Alberta, Canada, (main supervisor; co-supervised with Abram Hindle)

Ph.D.

Kristen Newbury 2018–Present

University of Alberta, Canada Master's

Erick Ochoa 2017–Present

University of Alberta, Canada, (main supervisor; co-supervised with José Nelson Amaral)

Master's

Stefan Krüger 2015–Present

University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden)

Ph.D.

Lisa Nguyen 2015–Present

University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden)

Ph.D.

ALUMNI

Johannes Späth 2019

University of Paderborn, Germany, (co-supervised with Eric Bodden)

Research Associate at Fraunhofer IEM

• Ph.D. Thesis: Synchronized Pushdown Systems for Pointer and Data-Flow Analysis

Manuel Benz 2016

TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY

Master's Thesis: Interprocedural Data Dependency Graphs

Ph.D. at University of Paderborn

Master's Thesis. Interprocedural bata bependency Graphs

Michael Appel 2016

TECHNISCHE UNIVERSITÄT DARMSTADT, GERMANY

• Master's Thesis: Call Graph Summaries for the Android SDK

Teaching.

INSTRUCTOR

CMPUT 497	Foundations of Program Analysis, University of Alberta, Canada	Winter 2019-Present
CMPUT 229	Computer Organization and Architecture I, University of Alberta, Canada	Winter 2017-Present
CMPUT 620	Static Program Analysis, University of Alberta, Canada	Fall 2016–Present
SAS	Static Analysis Seminar. Technische Universität Darmstadt. Germany	Winter 2015

Co-Instructor

APSA Applied Static Analysis, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany Spring 2016

SUBSTITUTE LECTURER

DECA	Designing Code Analyses for Large Software Systems, Technische Universität Darmstadt, Germany	Winter 2014
CS 241	Foundations of Sequential Programs, University of Waterloo, Canada	Spring 2013

GRADUATE TEACHING ASSISTANT

CS 241	Foundations of Sequential Programs, University of Waterloo, Canada	2011–2013
CS 444/644	Compiler Construction, University of Waterloo, Canada	2011–2013
CS 446/646	Software Design and Architectures, University of Waterloo, Canada	Spring 2011
CS 456/656	Computer Networks, University of Waterloo, Canada	2008–2010
CS 125	Introduction to Programming Principles, University of Waterloo, Canada	Winter 2008
CS 448	Security Engineering, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	Fall 2007

Undergraduate Teaching Assistant

CS 448	Security Engineering, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	Fall 2007
CS 330	Computer Architecture, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	2005–2006
CS 106	Fundamentals of Computer Science, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	2004–2005

Volunteer Work _____

Reverse EXPO Co-Organizer, University of Alberta, Canada	2018-Present
CyberPatriot Technical Mentor, Strathcona High School, Edmonton, Alberta, Canada	2016-2018
Graduate Student Ambassador, University of Waterloo, Canada	Fall 2013
Tour Guide, Computer Science Open House, University of Waterloo, Canada	Winter 2012
President, Egyptian Students Association, University of Waterloo, Canada	2010-2011
Ushers Committee Leader, Honors Assembly, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	Spring 2007
Academic Committee Head, ACM Chapter, The American University in Cairo, Egypt	Spring 2007